Guide to the Samuel Proal Hatfield Civil War Photograph Album, 1861 - 1865
Samuel Proal Hatfield Civil War Photograph Album, 1861 - 1865
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Hatfield, Samuel P.
1000-92
2.0
1
Samuel Proal Hatfield was a non-graduate of Wesleyan in the class of 1862. He enlisted as private, 4th Conn. Infantry in 1861. He then served as First Lieutenant, 1st Conn. Heavy Artillery from 1862-64, and later served as major of the same.
This photograph album of the 4th Connecticut Volunteers, Company G (later renamed the 1st Connecticut Heavy Artillery) is an informative collection of well-known and historically significant photographs, maps and drawings of battles, forts, geographic locations, and people divided into eight sections. Locations photographed are primarily in Virginia, including Yorktown, Fredericksburg, Petersburg, Broadway Landing, the Peninsular Campaign, and the Bermuda Hundred area. There are also photographs from Fort Fisher, North Carolina.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Given to Wesleyan University by Samuel Proal Hatfield in 1915.
Biographical Note
Samuel Proal Hatfield was a non-graduate of Wesleyan in the class of 1862. He enlisted as private, 4th Conn. Infantry in 1861. He then served as First Lieutenant, 1st Conn. Heavy Artillery from 1862-64, and later served as major of the same.
Collection Overview
In researching Civil War photographs, many photos in this album were found in books and authoritative websites attributed to various well known Civil War photographers such as George Bernard and Matthew Brady. None of the photographs in this album are identified and credited to its photographer by Samuel Hatfield. This album is an informative collection of well-known and historically significant photographs, maps and drawings of battles, forts, geographic locations, and people divided into eight sections.
Part I
Section I: Hartford, CT camp to Connecticut River, vicinity of Hagerstown, Funkstown, Williamsport, Falling Waters, Maryland and vicinity of Harpers Ferry, Alexandria and Hampton, Virginia.
Section II: Yorktown, VA
Section III: Peninsular Campaign
Section IV: Fredericksburg
Part II: Broadway Landing, Seige Train Depot and Headquarters
Section V: Petersburg Lines
Section VI: Our Mortar
Section VII: Bermuda Hundred & James River
Section VIII: Fort Fisher
Inside front cover of album has note adhered to the page that reads:
"Presented to the Library of Wesleyan University 1915. Co. G, 4th Connecticut Volunteers was organized by the students and mustered into State service in April. The regiment was offered to the United States as part of the State contingent of troops for three months' service. It was not accepted as such, but its services were requested for three years, to which the regiment agreed and were so mustered May 22, 1861. It was the first regiment mustered into the United States service for the long term. The designation was changed in January 1862, to 1st Connecticut Heavy Artillery and as such served through the war.
"This album shows some of the scenes through which the regiment and students from the University passed, and may be of interest as a record of the peculiar nature of its (Artillery) services.
It is desired to be of record that, of the students thus engaged, at the last, in the breaking of the Confederate line at Fort Mahone, Petersburg, April 2, 1865, the University was actively represented and the supply of ammunition to the Union troops maintained through the day, when repeated attacks were made to recover the fort. By breaking the Confederate line here, Richmond was evacuated that night and the Confederacy dissolved like a broken bubble. Wesleyan was part of the bayonet point that broke it up, and the Union was saved. S.P. Hatfield, Class of 1862
Collection Arrangement
Each photograph is listed in the order it appears in the album.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865 --Battlefields --Pictorial works.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865 --Connecticut.; Connecticut--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Virginia--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; Yorktown (Va.)--History.; Fredericksburg, Battle of, Fredericksburg, Va., 1862.; Petersburg (Va.)--History.; Broadway (Va.)--History.; Bermuda Hundred Region (Va.)--History, Military.; Fort Fisher (N.C.: Fort)--Siege, 1864-1865.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Alumni and alumnae.; Photographs.; United States. Army. Connecticut Artillery Regiment, 1st (1861-1865); Peninsular Campaign, 1862.; Hatfield, Samuel P.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Part 1, Section I: Hartford, CT camp to Connecticut River, vicinity of Hagerstown, Funkstown, Williamsport, Falling Waters, Maryland and vicinity of Harpers Ferry, Alexandria and Hampton, Virginia.
  - First march June 10, 1861 from camp at Fishfry St., Hartford, CT North to Main St. West on Main St., Hartford, CT and South to the end of State St. to the Connecticut River.
  - Service began for the regiment in the vicinity of Hagerstown, Funkstown, Williamsport and Falling Waters, MD. Area around Alexandria, VA with fort locations highlighted.
  - Unidentified Volunteer
  - Lt. Jimmy Bunce
  - Major L.G. Hemingway
  - Capt. G.P. Mason
  - Photographs of Fort Scott and Fort Richardson, October 1906
  - Round, George C., Co. G, Lieut. U.S. Signal Corps. (Wesleyan University 1866 Round, George C.)
  - Harpers Ferry, VA., US Arsenal, 1861
  - Col. R.O. Tyler
  - Capt. & Bvt. Major B.P. Learned
  - Maryland heights, Harpers Ferry, VA
  - Fort Richardson, VA. Regiment arrived Oct. 9, 1861 and camped in the field.
  - Regiment marching out to parade, 1861.
  - Capt. Thomas S. Gilbert
  - Major H.H. Pierce
  - Photo of men at their cannons in the field: Chaplain Walker, Commissary Robins, Sarg. Skinner, Q.M. Washburn, Lt. Col. White, Col. Tyler, Major Hemingway, Asst. Sarg. Doule, Adjt. Trumbull, 2 unidentified orderlies.
  - Photo of men at their cannons in the field: Col. White, Major Hemingway, Major Kellogg, Capt. Gilbert, Lt. Cummings, Lt. Osborne, Capt. Burbank, Lt. Pierce, Capt. Rockwood, Lt. Ed. Gillette, Capt. Williams, Lt. Gribbons, Lt. Baldwin, Sargt. Hatfield.
  - Artillery drill in Ft. Richardson, March 1862.
  - 1st Connecticut Artillery Infantry drill near Fort Barnard, VA, 1863.
  - Capt. F.A. Pratt
  - Lt. John O'Brien
  - Formed square front rows kneeling.
  - Artillary drilling Fort Ward, 1863.
  - Sargeant, George D., Capt. (Wesleyan University n1862 Left college during senior year. Sergeant in Co. G, 4th Conn. Infantry, 1861. First lieutenant, Ist Conn Heavy Artillery; captain; brevet major.)
  - Lt. E.P. Mason
  - Group photo in front of quarters at Fort Ward 1863. Black adolescent sitting on steps by the men. Harwood, Hemingway, Rockwood, Gillette.
  - Capt. D.R. Hubbard
  - Capt. George F. Bill
  - Group photo of men in front of Capt. J. Perkins quarters at Fort Ward. Bulkley, Pardee, J. Perkins, Dimock, Osborne.
  - Hemingway, Major and his white horse at Fort. Ward, 1863.
  - Lt. S.A. Woodruff
  - Drawing of the original Monitor as laying off camp at Hampton, VA, April 1862 after the fight with the Merrimac.
  - Drawing of showing the pass at Lane Bridge.
- Section II: Yorktown, VA
  - Map of Reconnaissance of the session Works at Yorktown, VA, May 4, 1862.
  - Official Plan of the Seige of Yorktown, VA., April 5 to May 3, 1862.
  - Lt. F.J. Jones
  - Battery No. 1 Yorktown-Union, April 1862. Two 200-pdr Parrot guns and five 100-pdr.
  - Photo of a confederate gun has burst.
  - Confederate Fort Magrude, Gloucester Pt. View of ships on the water.
  - Confederate gun Yorktown Land front.
  - John C. Taylor, Company B
  - Union battery No.1 Yorktown.
  - Capt. G.P. Mason
  - 10-13 inch mortars - Union.
  - Lt. L.W. Jackson
  - Battery 4 Yorktown, VA, April 1862 Company's F and G.
  - Courthouse in Yorktown, VA, 1862.
  - Inside S.E. Angle Confederate Works. Gun had burst wreck of carriage.
  - Battery 4 Yorktown, Jackson, Harmon, Douglas.
  - Burst Confederate gun thrown out on slope.
  - Gloucester point, Battery Magruder, Confederate.
  - Along the bluff / river front Confederate guns.
  - Bastian at angle, Yorktown, Confederate.
  - Burst Confederate gun.
  - 1st Connecticut Artillery and siege train just before going up the river to join McClellans Army of Potomac for peninsula Campaign May 16, 1862.
  - Union battery No. 4 Yorktown, 10-13 inch mortars, Gibbons, Harmon, Brooker, Douglas and Jackson.
  - Cornwallis cave.
  - Inside of angle of river and land fronts Yorktown Confederate Works.
  - Confederate guns on bluff of York River.
  - Entrance to Yorktown Works Northwest side.
  - Confederate guns on bluff of river, Yorktown.
  - Confederate Works battery without guns, Yorktown.
  - Wharf in Yorktown, U.S.Q.M Dept. May 1862.
  - Siege train gathered for shipment, Yorktown, May 1862. Brooker, Ager, Faxon, S.H. Perkins, Gilbert, Sedgwick, Hatfield.
  - Capt. John Burton
  - Confederate Water Battery, Yorktown, VA, Faxon, Hatfield.
  - Steamer "Robert Morris" waiting to take 1st Connecticut Artillery up York River. Dock built by 1st Connecticut Artillery to ship siege train. Company's L & M remaining to care for guns and material.
  - Lt. J. Cummings
  - Lt. Robert Lewis
  - Cornwallis Cave, Yorktown, Ager, Burton, Doull (Major 4th NY Artillery) Sedgwick, S.H. Perkins, Hatfield, Brooker, Gilbert, Cornwallis Cave was originally used by Lord Cornwallis during the Revolutionary War and used by Confederates as a magazine.
  - Confederate General Magruder's Headquarters, Yorktown, VA 1862.
  - Moore House where Cornwallis signed surrender in 1781, Yorktown, VA.
  - Headquarters of Lord Cornwallis, Yorktown, VA.
  - Farnholdt House to the left of Battery No. 1.
  - Street in Yorktown, 1862.
  - The left of battery No. 1, Yorktown. Two 200pdr Parrots at left. Occupied by Company B, 1st Connecticut Artillery.
- Section III: Peninsular Campaign
  - Campaign maps, Army of the Potomac Map No. 3 White House to Harrison Landing, Peninsula Campaign, 1862.
  - The White House at Pamunkey River where the 1st Connecticut Artillery landed after leaving Yorktown, VA.
  - Corduroying a road.
  - Hotel at Old Church (Lipscomb's).
  - Landing above Yorktown, VA.
  - Bridge over Chickahominy River.
  - Ruins of Gaines Mill.
  - House on Fair Oaks battlefield near 1st Conn. Camp. June 27, 1862.
  - Fair Oaks, Company I at house June 27, 1862.
  - Battery on Fair oaks front near Company I.
  - Ruins of railroad bridge over Pamunkey River near White House. Destroyed June 28, 1862.
  - Balloon Army of Potomac, INTREPID, and another ballon near camp at Grains Mill.
  - Westover James River.
  - Twin houses at Fair Oaks.
  - Company K's 8 inch Howitzer near twin houses.
  - Men working on Grapevine Bridge over Chickahominy River.
  - Field hospital, Savage Station, wounded from Graines Mill, June 28, 1862.
  - Savage Station.
  - Battery at Fair oaks.
  - Wounded from Gaines Mill - Co. I passed here about the time picture was taken. These were captured by the Confederates very soon after picture was taken.
  - Fair Oaks Line near where Co. I was posted. Co. I was on this front with two Whitworth guns.
  - Drawing of the Battle of Gaines Mill June 27-28, 1862.
  - Sketch accompanying Major Doull's report to Col. Tyler.
  - Summers Corps. Crossing the Chickahominy River May 30, 1862 at time of fair Oaks Battle. The 1st Connecticut Artillery was ready to cross but not called upon.
  - Malvern Hill.
  - Harrison House, James River.
  - View from Malvern Hill looking West.
  - Westover, James River.
  - Malvern House.
- Section IV: Fredericksburg
  - Small Battle of Fredericksburg map showing artillery positions.
  - Confederate Lines
  - Franklin's Crossing
  - Company B's guns, 4 ½ inch.
  - Frederickburg, VA, view of town across river.
  - Fredericksburg, VA view of tent encampment with town in background
  - Stone wall at Marye's Heights with Confederate dead in picture. Photo said to be taken 20 minutes after Sedgwick's Corps carried the hill. Company M was assisting from across the river.
- Part 2: Broadway Landing; Seige Train Depot and Headquarters. Section V: Petersburg Lines
  - Petersburg Lines, Union shown in red
  - Fort Sedgwick (aka Ft. Hell)
  - Along the Union lines
  - Union picket, sharpshooters
  - From right of Sedgwick, over it and to left
  - Ft. Sedgwick
  - Lieut. Jack Odell killed in Ft. Steadman March 25, 1865
  - Lieut. Tarbell
  - Dead Confederate soldier outside Ft. Mahone April 2, 1865
  - Fort Meikel
  - Fort Rice
  - Between Fort Rice and Fort Meikel
  - Near Fort Morton
  - Fort Stedman, Battery X
  - Between Fort Stedman and Fort McGilvery
  - Near the mine, Union line
  - Trumbull, Thomas S., Lieut-Col.
  - Major, Capt. Elisha S. Kellogg, Co. B; Col. 2nd Conn. Arty. Killed at Cold Harbor, VA, June 2, 1864
  - Work of the Petersburg Express
  - Railroad near Petersburg
  - 2nd Lt. William Charnley, Company L
  - Capt. Edward R. Allen, Company I
  - Company I Officers, Scott, Hatfield, Faxon, Knox, Allen
  - Sergeant Charles Huxford, Company I
- Section VI: Our Mortar
  - Chesterfield Battery
  - Battery 4 Yorktown
  - Mortar on railroad car, Lieut. Jackson leaning on side
  - Mortar and camp of Company I near Battery IV.
  - Mortar on platform with Company I men.
  - Capt. Pratt, Capt. Dow, Gen. Abbott, Gen. Hunt; Chief or Artillery, Army of Potomac, Lieut. Col. Trumbull
  - Mortar at Bridgeport on way to Hartford, CT.
  - Mortar monument at Capitol Grounds, Hartford, CT.
  - Hatfield, S.P. Major Ordnance officer
  - Lt. I.N. Westervelt, Lieut. Asst. Ordnance officer
  - Gillett, Corny., Asst. Ordnance officer
  - Seige Train Depot, Broadway landing, VA.
  - General H.L. Abbott
  - Faxon, W.C., Asst. Ordnance officer
  - Hough, Collis S., Sergeant Company C., built docks
  - Pontoon bridge and hospital boat, Appomattox River, VA
  - Westervelt, Hemingway, Ager, Hatfield, Learned, Abbot, Delevan, Skinner, Filer
  - Lt. C.E. Gillett
  - Headquarters Broadway Landing, VA. Faxon, Hatfield, Westervelt, Ager, Learned, Abbott, Jarvis, Skinner, Filer, Mason, Hemingway, Batterson
  - May 1865 captured gun on mortar wagon at Ordnance Depot, Broadway Landing, VA
  - At City Point after explosion of Ordnance Depot
  - City Point Line, Battery Abbott
  - Sling carts at Ordnance Depot, Broadway Landing
  - Bv't Capt. Charles W. Filer, The Mad Adjutant
  - Dutch Gap Canal, August 1864
- Section VII: Bermuda Hundred and James River
  - James River - Bermuda Line
  - Double turreted monitor Onondaga in James River near Dutch Gap
  - 10 inch S.C. mortars going into Battery Sawyer
  - Dutch Gap Canal, completed 1865
  - Signal Tower near Battery Sawyer, right of Bermuda Line
  - Bermuda Line, Redhoubt McConihe, VA
  - Bermuda Line, Redoubt Carpenter, VA
  - Battery Sawyer, VA Crow's Nest, shows S.B. Sawyer gun. (Burst June 1864 and replaced with 100-pdr parrot)
  - Redoubt Drake, VA
  - Redoubt Dutton, VA
  - Redoubt Weed, VA
  - Battery Pruyn, VA
  - Redoubt Anderson, VA
  - Howlett House, Battery Dantzler
  - Battery Wood
  - Battery Semmes
  - Battery Brooke
  - Union obstructions in the river 1864, near Battery Spofford
  - Sling carts
  - Fort Brady
  - Drewry's Bluff
  - Battery Abbot, near Ft. Brady
  - Fort Drewry
  - Capt. S.H. Perkins
  - Pontoon Bridge, James Landing, James River
  - Capt. W.A. Lincoln
  - Fort Burnham
  - Castle Thunder, Richmond, VA
  - Bomb proofs in N.E. Bastien
  - Capt. George Dimock
  - Lt. R.S. Douglass
  - Armstrong gun (English) in flank of N.E. Bastion
  - Mount Battery, 60 feet high
- Section VIII: Fort Fisher
  - Maps of Fort Fisher area showing position of Naval vessels during bombardment, captured Jan. 15, 1865 by Union forces.
  - Fort Fisher, North Carolina
  - William B. Ellis, Sergeant Co. I, Major 2nd Conn. Arty.
  - Major Charles O. Brigham
  - Lt. L.G. Logan
  - Commissary Office at Fort Fisher
  - Battery Buchanan
  - 7th, 8th & 9th traverses from N.E. angle
  - Burnside Bridge, Antietam
  - Sunken Road, Antietam, Confederate dead after charge by Union Irish Brigade
  - Along Hagerstown Rd., Antietam, Confederate dead